University of Connecticut 1989.0024
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
University of Connecticut Libraries Records
undated, 1882-
1989.0024
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
64.95 Linear feet
University of Connecticut. University of Connecticut Libraries.
Box 87
History
Prior to the construction of the Wilbur Cross Library, the institution's library was located first in Whitney [Old] Hall and then the Administration Building [Old Main]. With the construction of a new classroom building in 1929, the library was relocated to the newly named Beach Hall. The name change of the institution in 1939 coincided with the construction of the first building on campus intended to house only the University's library collection. The Wilbur Cross Library [now the Wilbur Cross Building] was the University's first library until the addition of branch, or regional, libraries as the University expanded across the state and the construction of the Homer D. Babbidge Library, which was completed and occupied in 1978.
The University Libraries include libraries on the regional campuses, such as those in Torrington and Stamford and special divisions on the Storrs campus such as the Pharmacy, Music & Dramatic Arts Libraries and Archives & Special Collections in the Dodd Research Center. The Health Center Library located in Farmington and the Law Library in Hartford are associated with the University Libraries but maintain separate budgets, administrative structures and technical services.
Scope and Content
The University of Connecticut Libraries (UCL) collection contains library office files from 1940-1994, including accession records dating back to 1882. The collection includes the files of university librarians, a staff member, and several directors of the university libraries, as well as meeting minutes, staff and personnel records, and records concerning the construction of Homer Babbidge Library.
The files and official records of several UCL committees, teams and affiliates have been included in this finding aid, as well.
Arrangement
The collection was transferred in several accessions beginning in 1982. More recent accessions have not yet been processed and are not represented in this finding aid.
Series I: University Librarian ( 1940-1956 ) contains the records of Paul Alcorn, and includes files on William Benton, the branch libraries, library budget matters, student assistants, and the War Information Library. Also included in this series are employment applications and correspondence. The series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
Series II: Director of University Libraries ( 1958-1994 ) contains the records of the Libraries' chief administrative officer. The series has divided further to represent the tenures of the individuals holding this title. Subseries A: James Skipper includes information pertaining to university branch libraries, the library budget, and cataloging systems. Subseries B: John McDonald includes information on library associations; acquisitions; management; automation; collection development; departmental meetings; equipment; policies, goals and objectives; grant proposals; and security. In addition, there are correspondence and budget files, staff memoranda, committee reports, and press releases. Subseries C: Norman Stevens documents accreditation, committees, collection development, use of databases, grants, goals, and objectives, staff matters, and technical services.
Series III: Vice Provost ( 1998- ) includes the records of the last administrator to hold the title of Director and the first to be named Vice Provost (Chancellor). These records have not yet been processed.
Subseries A: Paul Kobulnicky
Subseries B: Brinley Franklin
Series IV: Associate Directors ( 1970-1978 ) Subseries A: Information and Collection Services (David Kapp) includes information on administrative organization, the library budget, collection development, meetings, emergencies, programs and courses, micro/media, and technical services. In addition, there are departmental reports and correspondence. Materials from other Departments will be integrated as they are processed.
Series V: Areas ( ) includes those materials documenting the activities of the Library units as organized after the 1997 reorganization.
Series VI: Minutes ( 1961-1978 ) contains two subseries-- Subseries A: Administrative Meetings (1975-1978) and Subseries B: Department Head Meetings (1961-1975).
Series VII: Staff and Personnel ( undated ) includes staff association information and staff handbooks.
Series VIII: Book Accession Lists ( 1882-1960 ) contains accession information. This series is comprised of 20 volumes.
Series IX: Publications ( 1944-1983 ) is arranged in five subseries-- Subseries A: Bibliographies contains files on such subjects as aging, black religion and studies, crime, the Connecticut Bicentennial, education, microbiology, social sciences, textiles, and Vietnam. It also contains information on literary artists such as Erskine Caldwell and George Starbuck. Subseries B: Exhibits includes information on several specific library exhibits from the 1970s and 1980s. Subseries C: Guides is a section of publications containing Guide to the UCONN Library and Black Studies Guide. Subseries D: Readings contains brochures and flyers of readings given at UConn by poets such as Robert Creeley and Joan Joffee Hall. Subseries E: Other contains four publications, including The Librarian.
Series X: Staff Materials ( circa 1970 ) contains news articles, staff questionnaires and ballots, and materials on legal matters of interest to library staff, presumably collected by Linda Polcari, a member of the reference staff. The subject files are arranged alphabetically.
Series XI: Construction of Homer Babbidge Library ( 1969-1977 ) consists of files arranged chronologically followed by subject files which include building elements, funding requests, correspondence, design criteria, reports, and statistics. The subject files are arranged alphabetically.
Series XII: Library Development Office Records ( undated, 1988-1999 ) contains materials regarding the planning and funding of the "Dodd Year" and are restricted to Library Development staff only.
Series XIII: Committee Records ( 1974-2006 ) contains the records of the Libraries' working committees and teams. Subseries A: Advisory Council on the Evaulation and Promotion of Professional Librarians; Subseries B: Poetry Committee; Subseries C: User Team was established in 1997 to draft, conduct and evaluate a faculty and study survey of library services and collections. The final report was submitted to the Library in December 1997. In the 2009 Library reorganization it was renamed the Survey and Assessment Team.
Series XIV: Audiovisual materials ( 1996-2001 ).
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Photographs from this collection have been integrated into the University of Connecticut Photograph Collection. Please request those materials if you wish to see related images.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Annual Reports Dodd Periodicals
Harvest Dodd Periodicals
The Librarian Dodd Periodicals
Library Bulletin Dodd Periodicals
Health Retirement Dinner 1989-0024.vr1
Sue's Party 1989-0024.vr2
Restrictions on Access
With the exception of the Library Development Office Records, there are no access restrictions on this collection.
Custodial History
The records of the various Library divisions are maintained by those areas separately until their transfer to the University Archives.
Acquisition Information
The records have been transferred to the Archives periodically.
University of Connecticut.; Academic libraries--Connecticut.; Administrative records.; Audio cassettes.; Audio visual materials.; Blueprints.; Books.; Bylaws.; Connecticut.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Financial Records.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Library buildings--United States--Design and construction.; Maps.; Minutes.; Newsletters.; Newspapers.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Publications.; Speeches.; State universities and colleges--United States.; Storrs (Conn.); Universities and colleges--Administration.; Universities and colleges--United States.; Universities and colleges.; University of Connecticut. Libraries--Employees.; University of Connecticut. Libraries.; Videocassettes.; Works of Art.
- Series I: University Librarian, 1940-1956
  - Alcorn, Paul
    - Personal
      - 1949-1950 (Box 1)
      - 1950-1951
      - 1951-1952
      - 1953-1955
  - American Mathematical Society, undated
  - Benton, William, undated
  - Birk Collection, undated
  - Book Orders, 1954-1955
  - Branches, 1950-1954
  - Budget, 1954
  - Connecticut Library Association
  - Correspondence
    - 1940-1946
    - 1952-1955
    - Alcorn, Paul, 1948-1950
    - General, 1944-1945
    - General, 1950-1955
  - Duplicates: listed December, 1949, 1949-1950 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Letter, 1950
  - Faculty Book Requests, 1951-1952
  - Faculty Requests, 1954
  - F.J. Bernard and Co., undated
  - Franklin, Burt, 1950-1951
  - Furniture, 1950-1951
  - Gifts and Exchanges, 1950-1951
  - Graduate School, 1954
  - Graduate School Committee, 1949-50, 1950-1951
  - I.G. Davis Room, 1950-1951
  - Interdepartmental Correspondence, 1942-1943
  - Inter-Office Correspondence, 1950-1952
  - Inventory, 1951-1954
  - Kraus Periodicals, Inc., 1950-1954
  - Laumonier Library, 1951-1952
  - Library Committee, 1951-1952
  - Mayfair Agency, 1950-1951
  - Microfilm, 1950-1951
  - Moore-Cottrell Subscription Agencies, 1950-1951
  - National Library Bindery Co., 1950-1951
  - Nijhoff, Martinus, 1950-1951
  - Out-of-Print Book Lists, 1950-1951
  - Plant Maintenance, 1951-1954
  - Poems, etc., undated
  - Prentice-Hall, Inc., 1950-1951
  - President's Office, 1950-1955
  - Provost's Office, 1951-1955
  - Reports, undated
  - Statistics/Surveys, 1951-1953
  - Stechert - Hafner, 1950-1951
  - Summer Sessions, undated
  - Victory Book Campaign, undated
  - War Information Library, undated
- Series II: Director of University Libraries, 1958-1994
  - Subseries A: James Skipper, 1958-1962
    - Branches
      - Hartford, undated (Box 3)
      - Stamford, undated
      - Torrington, undated
      - Waterbury, undated
    - Budget, 1961-1963
    - Cataloging: Cutter System, undated
    - Law Library, undated
    - Metcalf Survey, undated
  - Subseries B: John McDonald, 1963-1986
    - AAUP ( American Association of University Professors), undated (Box 4)
    - AACR2, undated
    - Accessions List System, undated
    - ACEP (Advisory Council on Evaluation and Promotion), undated
    - Acquisitions, undated
    - ACRL ( Association of College and Research Libraries), undated
    - ACRL - ARL ( Association of Research Libraries), undated
    - Academic Libraries of Connecticut, undated
    - Academic Status, undated
    - Ad Hoc Administrative Planning Committee, undated
    - Administrative Organization, undated
    - Affirmative Action, undated
    - ALA ( American Library Association), undated
    - Alternative Library, undated
    - American Antiquarian Society, undated
    - Annual Department Reports, 1979-1982
    - Annual Report Notes, undated
    - ARL
      - Association of Research Libraries, undated
      - Ad Hoc Committee on Machine-Based Materials, undated
      - Inter-Library Loan, undated
      - Management Study, undated
      - Management Survey, undated
      - Shared Cataloging Committee, undated
      - Title II - A Awards, undated
    - ARL - MRAP
      - Correspondence with University Personnel, undated (Box 5)
      - Initial MRAP Survey, undated
    - Art Catalog: Correspondence, undated
    - Asian Students, undated
    - Audio - Visual, undated
    - Automated Circulation Control, undated
    - Automation, Seminar in, undated
    - Bar Code Database Cleanup Group, 1986
    - Bibliography for Proposed Graduate Reading Room, 1971
    - Black Studies, Committee on, undated
    - Book Collection Contest: Essays of Winners, 1971
    - Book Sale, 1983
    - Branches
      - Hartford, undated
      - Southeastern at Avery Point, undated
      - Stamford, undated
      - Torrington, undated
      - Waterbury, undated
      - Waterbury, Hewitt (Apiary) Collection, undated
    - Budget
      - 1963-1965
      - 1965-1967
      - 1967-1969
      - 1968-1969
      - 1969-1971
      - 1971-1973
      - 1973-1974
      - Task Force, undated
    - CAL ( Council of Automated Libraries), undated
    - Cataloging, undated
    - Censorship, undated
    - Censorship and Academic Freedom, undated
    - Census Tapes, undated
    - Centennial Plaza, undated
    - CIT (Circulation Implementation Team), undated
    - Circulation/Reserve Room, undated
    - CLA ( Connecticut Library Association, undated
    - CLA, Development Committee, undated
    - Collective Bargaining, undated
    - Collection Development, undated
    - Collection Development, Staff Meetings, undated
    - College Catalog, undated
    - College of the Virgin Islands, undated
    - Commission on University Governance, undated
    - Committee on Faculty Status, undated
    - Committees, General, undated
    - Committees and Meetings, undated
    - Compustat Tapes, undated (Box 6)
    - Computer Center Advisory Committee, 1980-1987
    - Computer Efficiency Ad Hoc Committee, 1985
    - Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, undated
    - Connecticut Alumnus, undated
    - Connecticut Regional Medical Program, undated
    - Connecticut State Library Research Center, undated
    - Connecticut Advisory Committee, 1986
    - Connecticut Union List of Serials, undated
    - Cooperative Library Service Unit Review Board, 1982
    - Cooperative Program Planning for the New England Land Grant Universities, undated
    - Copyright Committee, 1984
    - Correspondence, Administration, undated
    - Correspondence, Consultant, undated
    - Council of Deans, undated
    - Council on Human Rights and Opportunities, undated
    - CRLC (Capital Region Library Council), 1978-1985
    - Decentralization, undated
    - Dedication, undated
    - Department Head Meetings, undated
    - Deposit Catalog, undated
    - ECLA ( Eastern Connecticut Library Association), 1983-1984
    - ELCA, Automation Committee, 1982-1983
    - ECLANET, undated
    - Education Technology Joint Committee, Information Retrieval and Task Force, 1983
    - Emeritus Staff, undated
    - Engineering, undated
    - Environment and Man, Center for, undated
    - E.O. Smith High School Library, undated
    - Equipment List
      - Index, undated
      - Basement, undated
      - Plaza, undated
      - First Floor, undated
      - Second Floor, undated
      - Third Floor, undated
      - Fourth Floor, undated
    - Etherington Report, undated
    - Evaluation Team Minutes, 1983-1984
    - Experimental College, undated
    - Faculty for Rational Alternatives, undated
    - Faculty Status, undated
    - Fan Mail, undated
    - Federal Documents Regional Conference, undated
    - Formula Budgeting, undated
    - Freedom to Read Seminar, undated
    - Friends of the Library, undated
    - Geographic Information System, undated
    - GIP (GEAC Implementation) Committee Minutes, undated
    - Gifts to the Library, 1982-1984
    - Goals and Objectives, undated
    - Governance, undated
    - Government Publications, undated
    - Government Publications Department Task Force, 1981-1982
    - Government Publications Department Task Force Report, undated (Box 7)
    - Governor's Committee on Libraries, undated
    - Graduate Center, undated
    - Graduate Students, undated
    - Grant Proposals, undated
      - ConnLinet, undated
      - Gaines, undated
      - Geigel, undated
      - LSCA (Library Services and Construction Act), undated
    - Growth and Development Community Seminar, 1982-1983
    - Hartford Seminary Foundation, undated
    - Health Center Library, undated
    - Health Center Library, Clinical Librarians in-patient Care/Teaching Settings, undated
    - Higher Education Act Amendments, undated
    - History/Centennial, undated
    - Industrial Information Service, undated
    - Inner College, undated
    - Institute of International and Intercultural Studies, undated
    - Institute of World Affairs, undated
    - Insurance, Library Collection, undated
    - Interdepartmental Correspondence, undated
    - International Federation of Libraries Association, 1972-1979 (Box 8)
    - International Book Year, 1972
    - Inventory, undated
    - Italian Studies Institute, undated
    - Latin American Colloquium Newsletter, undated
    - Law Library, undated
    - Learning Resources and Technology Advisory Council, undated
    - Legislation, undated
    - Leiberman vs. Gant, 1982
    - Librarian for Human Rights and Opportunities, undated
    - Library Addition Equipment Lists, undated
    - Library Advisory Committee, undated
    - Library Committee for Relocation, School of Nursing and Allied Health Professions, 1984
    - Library Committee on University Governance, undated
    - Library Course, undated
    - Library Exhibition, undated
    - Library History and Development, undated
    - Library Instruction Program Committee, 1983-1985
    - Library Personnel Procedures and Affirmative Action, 1973
    - Library Resources Committee, 1984
    - Loan Regulations of Other Universities, undated
    - Long Range Planning, undated
    - Mary Mahoney Room, undated
    - Master Plan, undated
    - Master Plan for Higher Education, undated
    - MBA Library, undated
    - Memoranda, General, undated
    - Memoranda to Department Heads, undated
    - Memoranda to Staff, undated
    - Microtext Materials, undated
    - Mission Statement, Library, undated
    - Misuse of Library Material Ad Hoc Committee, 1982-1984
    - MRAP (Management Review and Analysis Program), undated
      - Administration and Organization, undated
      - Budget and Finance, undated
      - Classified, undated
      - Correspondence with ARL Office, undated
      - Correspondence with Library Staff, undated (Box 9)
      - Correspondence with Study Team, undated
      - Evaluation of Program, undated
      - Implementation Committee Election, undated
      - MIS Task Force, undated
      - Planning, Library, undated
      - Planning, University, undated
      - Planning Task Force, undated
      - Space, undated
      - Study Team Work Sheets, undated
    - MRMS, 1985-1986
    - Music Library, undated
    - Music Library Advisory Committee, 1982-1983
    - National Agricultural Library Association, 1971-1974
    - National Foundation on Arts and Humanities, 1965-1966
    - NECL, undated
    - NELA ( New England Library Association, 1970-1971
    - NELB ( New England Library Board), 1981-1982
    - NELB, Panel of Counselors, 1979-1980
    - NELINET, undated
    - NELINET, Ad Hoc Committee on Pricing, 1981-1983
    - NELINET; OCLC Inc. Users Council, 1983-1985
    - NERAC ( New England Research Application Center, undated
    - NERAC, Application for Research Grant, undated
    - NERAC, SDI (Selective Dissemination of Information), undated
    - New Library Status, Finance, undated
    - New Rural Society Project, undated
    - Non-Print Media Integration: A Proposal, 1973 (Box 10)
    - Ockenden Report, undated
    - One Millionth Book Celebration, 1971
    - Oral History, undated
    - Orientation Committee, 1975-1979
    - PALS (Planning for and Automated Library System) Minutes, 1983-1984
    - Pharmacy Library, undated
    - Photoduplication and Microtext, undated
    - Pilot Project for the Development of a Connecticut Union List of Serials, undated
    - Planned Acquisitions Project, undated
    - Planned Advisory Committee, undated
    - Planning Advisory Committee, Subcommittee on Divisional Science Library, undated
    - Planning Process, Phase I and II, 1983
    - Pomfret School, undated
    - Press Releases, undated
    - Promotional Policies and Procedures Committee, 1971
    - Public Services, undated
    - Public Services Council, undated
    - Publications Committee, 1972-1986
    - Racism, undated
    - Reading Resources Network Center, undated
    - Reference, undated
    - Renovation, undated
    - Report of the Subcommittee for the Study of Library Development, 1968
    - Roy E. Jones Poultry Library Committee, 1981
    - Salaries, undated
    - Schertz Report, 1969
    - SECLA ( Southeastern Connecticut Library Association), undated
    - Security, undated
    - Semester on the Thirties, undated
    - Senate Growth and Development, Space Assignment Committee, 1979
    - Serials, undated
    - Serials Subscription Committee, undated
    - SLA ( Special Library Association), 1979
    - Social Inquiry Faculty Advisory Committee, 1981 (Box 11)
    - Social Work Library, undated
    - Southeastern Library Network, 1974-1985
    - Southern Connecticut State Library, 1975-1978
    - Space Needs and Present Deficiencies, undated
    - Space Survey of ARL Libraries, undated
    - Special Collections, undated
    - Spring Festival in the Library, 1973
    - Staff Notes, undated
    - State Technical Services, undated
    - Statistics, undated
    - Student Book Collection Contest, undated
    - Student Demonstrations, undated
    - Target, 1971
    - Technical Services, undated
    - Telefacsimile Experiment, undated
    - Teletype Network Standards Committee, 1974
    - Thackery Collection, undated
    - Traffic and Parking Advisory Committee, undated
    - ULA (University Library Assistants) Advisory Council, 1974-1980
    - University Council on Human Rights and Opportunities, undated
    - University Libraries, Programs, undated
    - University Library Communication Center Advisory Committee, 1977
    - Unprocessed MacDonald materials, undated, 1950s-1980s
    - Vacation and Sick Leave Policy, undated
    - Value Engineering, undated
    - Vietnam Moratorium Day, undated
    - Vincent Project, undated
    - Water Resources, undated
    - Wilbur Cross Library Report, undated
    - Zarrow, M.X. Memorial Fund, undated
  - Subseries C: Norman Stevens, 1979-1995
    - Academic Librarians in State Service, undated (Box 12)
    - Accreditation, undated
    - ACEP (Advisory Council on Evaluation and Promotion of Professional Librarians), 1986-1987
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Eating, Drinking and Smoking, 1987
    - ARL ( Association of Research Libraries), undated
    - CLA ( Connecticut Library Association), undated
    - Collection Development, undated
    - Committees, undated
    - CTUW, undated
    - Database Searching, undated
    - DIT (Database Implementation Team), 1986
    - ECLANET, undated
    - Fan Mail, undated
    - Friends of the Library, undated
    - Friends of the Library, Executive Board Minutes, undated
    - Goals and Objectives, undated (Box 13)
    - Grant Proposals, undated
      - ConnLinet, undated
      - LSCA, undated
    - Interagency Library Planning Committee, 1986
    - Interdepartmental Letters, undated
    - Library Advisory Committee, undated
    - Library Exhibition Committee, undated
    - Library Instruction Program Committee, 1987
    - Long Range Plan Library, undated
    - Merit Criteria Committee, undated
    - Organization, Library, 1986
    - PC Users Club, 1987
    - Public Services Council, undated
    - Serials Subscription Committee, undated
    - Staff Association, 1986
    - Systems Advisory Committee, 1986-1987
    - Technical Services Reorganization Task Force, 1987
    - Technical Services Workflow Committee, 1986-1987